舰长
Captain.
- 方便说话吗？ - 说吧
- Got a minute? - A minute.
你有没有觉得史波克有点不对劲
It's Spock. You noticed anything strange about him?
没感觉，为什么这么说？
No, nothing in particular. Why?
虽然彻底检查之前我不能确定
Well, it's nothing I can pinpoint without an examination,
但是他现在越来越躁动
but he's become increasingly restive.
如果他不是瓦肯，那可以说是“紧张”
If he were not a Vulcan, I'd almost say "nervous."
另外他现在拒绝进食
For another thing, he's avoiding food.
我确认他已经三天没吃东西了
I've checked and he hasn't eaten at all in three days.
听起来史波克先生进入冥想阶段了
Well, that just sounds like Mr. Spock in one of his contemplative phases.
查佩尔小姐
Miss Chapel.
- 麦考伊医生 - 舰长
- Dr. McCoy. - Captain.
这是什么？
What's this?
瓦肯族的普罗米克汤，肯定是你做的吧
Vulcan plomeek soup. And I'll bet you made it too.
你从来不死心，不是吗？
You never give up hoping, do you?
我只是碰巧发现史波克先生没有吃东西
Mr. Spock hasn't been eating, Doctor. And I just happened to notice.
没关系，你去吧，查佩尔小姐
It's all right. Carry on, Miss Chapel.
- 老骨头，我要去忙了 - 吉姆
- Bones, I'm a busy man. - Jim,
我建议史波克进行常规体检的时候
when I suggested to Spock it was time for his routine checkup
你理智的大副对我说
your logical, unemotional first officer turned to me and said:
立刻停止对我的窥探，医生
"You will cease to pry into my personal matters, Doctor,
否则我扭断你的脖子
or I shall certainly break your neck."
史波克这么说？
Spock said that?
这是什么破东西
What is this?
又是监视，窥探，如果有需要，我自己会说的
Poking. Prying. If I want anything from you, I'll ask for it.
舰长，我想请假回自己的星球
Captain, I should like to request a leave of absence. On my home planet.
从现行轨道绕去瓦肯，只会损失2.8光天
On our present course, you can divert to Vulcan with a loss of but 2.8 light-days.
- 到底出了什么鬼事？ - 我已经提出请求了，舰长
- What the devil is this all about? - I've made my request, Captain.
我只要你一个答案，允许还是不允许
All I require from you is that you answer it, yes or no.
宇宙，最后的边疆
Space, the final frontier.
这是星舰进取号的航程
These are the voyages of the starship Enterprise.
它的五年任务，是去探索未知的新世界
Its five-year mission: To explore strange new worlds,
找寻新的生命与新的文明
to seek out new life and new civilizations,
勇敢的航向前人未至之境
to boldly go where no man has gone before.
【星际迷航：原初】
-=THE LAST FANTASY=-
荣誉出品
本字幕仅供学习交流，严禁用于商业途径
-=TLF字幕组=-
翻译：gosiwi
校对：喜马拉雅
第二季第一集
狂躁时刻
好，史波克，说吧
All right, Spock. Let's have it.
取悦一个陌生男性，对女人来说有点不检点
It is undignified for a woman to play servant to a man who is not hers.
我们还是聊聊你的请假吧
I'm more interested in your request for shore leave.
- 根据这些年… - 你已经知道我的请求
- In the years that I've known... - You have my request.
你批准吗？
Will you grant it or not?
根据这些年我对你的了解，你从未要求请假
In all the years I've known you, you've never asked for leave of any sort.
你甚至拒绝了，为什么现在要请假？
In fact, you've refused them. Why now?
舰长，显然我已经积累了足够的假期
Captain, surely I have enough leave time accumulated.
没错，但这不是主要问题，是吗？
Agreed. But that isn't the question, is it?
如果出现一些情况，比如家人重病…
If there's a problem of some sort, illness in the family...
没有
No.
没有那回事，舰长
Nothing of that nature, Captain.
那我们就去牛郎星6号行星
Then since we're headed for Altair VI,
而且星球上有先进的设备…
and since the shore facilities there are excellent...
不，我必须…
No. I must...
我希望能请假去瓦肯
I wish to take my leave on Vulcan.
史波克，我问你
Spock, I'm asking you.
出什么事了？
What's wrong?
我需要休息
I need rest.
请你接受这个回答
I'm asking you to accept that answer.
舰桥
Bridge.
- 舵手 - 是，舰长
- Helm. - Yes, Captain?
转向去瓦肯
Alter course to Vulcan.
- 加速到曲速四 - 是，长官
- Increase speed to warp 4. - Aye, sir.
谢谢舰长
Thank you, Captain.
看来大部分人都没意识到瓦肯人也有脆弱的时候
I suppose most of us overlook the fact that even Vulcans aren't indestructible.
是的
No.
我们不是坚不可摧的
We're not.
舰长日志，星历3372.7
Captain's Log, Stardate 3372.7.
如计划行驶，经瓦肯前往牛郎星6号行星
On course, on schedule, bound for Altair VI via Vulcan.
大副史波克似乎压力巨大
First Officer Spock seems to be under stress.
他要求请假去瓦肯并已获批
He has requested and been granted shore leave.
麦考伊医生已在监护他的身体状况
Ship's Surgeon McCoy has him under medical surveillance.
舰长，舰队频道上有情况
Captain, something's coming in on the Starfleet channel.
紧急状况，长官
Priority and urgent, sir.
传过来，上尉
Put it on audio over here, Lieutenant.
消息转换完毕
Message complete, sir. Switching over.
星际舰队第9分队致联邦星舰进取号舰长
To Captain, U.S.S. Enterprise. From Starfleet, Sector 9.
牛郎星6号就职典礼提前7个太阳日
Inauguration ceremonies Altair VI have been advanced seven solar days.
现命令你按照要求改变飞行计划
You're ordered to alter your flight plan as filed to accommodate.
舰队司令部寇马克上将令
By order of Komack, Admiral, Starfleet Command.
收到
Acknowledge.
乌乎拉上尉，接受这个指令
Lieutenant Uhura, acknowledge that message.
是，长官
Aye aye, sir.
契诃夫先生，计算调整所需轨道和航速
Mr. Chekov, compute course and speed necessary for compliance.
我们必须以曲速六直趋前往
We'll have to head directly there at warp 6, sir.
没时间停留在瓦肯
Insufficient time to stop off at Vulcan.
直趋前往牛郎星6号
Head directly for Altair VI.
水手的运气，史波克先生
Sailor's luck, Mr. Spock.
简直就像墨菲定理：
Or, as one of Finagle's Laws puts it:
每艘船停留的港湾总是别人的家乡
"Any home port the ship makes will be somebody else's, not mine."
牛郎星6号的新总统想提前一周就职
The new President of Altair VI wants to get himself launched a week early,
所以我们必须提前到
so we have to be there a week early.
不要担心，我会给你假期的
Don't worry, I'll see that you get your leave,
一旦就职典礼结束
as soon as we're finished.
我完全理解，舰长
I quite understand, Captain.
- 舰桥，导航部 - 导航部，契诃夫
- Bridge, Navigation. - Navigation, Chekov here.
契诃夫，如果我们以最大速度绕道至瓦肯
Mr. Chekov, how late will we arrive for the ceremonies
把史波克丢上岸
if we increase speed to maximum and divert to Vulcan
最晚会什么时候达到典礼
just long enough to drop off Mr. Spock?
我不理解，舰长
I do not understand, Captain.
我们会耽搁多久？
How far behind schedule will diverting to Vulcan put us?
我们正在前往瓦肯，舰长，是史波克先生命令的
We're on course for Vulcan, Captain, as Mr. Spock ordered.
谢谢，契诃夫先生，寇克完毕
Thank you, Mr. Chekov. Kirk out.
史波克先生
Mr. Spock.
请跟我来
Come with me, please.
5号舱
Deck 5.
你为什么变更航道去瓦肯，史波克先生？
You changed course for Vulcan, Mr. Spock. Why?
变更航道？
Changed the course?
你否认吗？
Do you deny it?
不，一点不否认，舰长
No. By no means, Captain.
我很可能这么做了
It is quite possible.
- 为什么？ - 舰长，我承认你所说的…
- Then why did you do it? - Captain, I accept, on your word...
我这么做了
...that I did it.
但是我也不知道为什么，我也不记得我这么做了
But I do not know why, nor do I remember doing it.
舰长，把我锁起来吧
Captain, lock me away.
我不想见任何人
I do not wish to be seen.
瓦肯族人不能再做更多解释了
I cannot. No Vulcan could explain further.
我在帮你，史波克
I'm trying to help you, Spock.
别问了，我不会回答的
Ask me no further questions. I will not answer.
- 我命令你去医务室报道 - 医务室？
- I order you to report to the Sickbay. - Sickbay?
完成体检，麦考伊在等着
Complete examination. McCoy's waiting.
请进，史波克，我已经准备好了
Come in, Spock. I'm all ready for you.
我的命令是向医务室报道，医生
My orders were to report to Sickbay, Doctor.
我已经完成了
I have done so.
现在我要回自己的船舱
And now I'll go to my quarters.
我收到的命令是给你一个全面的体检
My orders were to give you a thorough physical.
也许你没意识到
In case you hadn't noticed,
给我们下命令的是同一个军官
I have to answer to the same commanding officer that you do.
来吧，史波克
Come on, Spock.
理智一点
Yield to the logic of the situation.
好吧
Very well.
给我体检吧，好让我们都交差
Examine me, for all the good it will do either of us.
你怎么想，契诃夫
How do you figure it, Chekov?
一开始，我们去瓦肯，然后我们去牛郎星
First we're going to Vulcan. Then we're going to Altair.
之后又要去瓦肯，这下又得去牛郎星
Then we're headed to Vulcan again. Now we're headed back to Altair.
我会晕舱的
I think I'm going to get space-sick.
吉姆，你必须送史波克去瓦肯
Jim, you've got to get Spock to Vulcan.
老骨头，我会的，一旦任务结束之后
Bones, I will, I will. As soon as this mission is completed.
现在，立刻，如果你不在一星期内把他送去瓦肯
No, now. Right away. If you don't get him to Vulcan within a week,
再在外面待八天，他就会死
eight days at the outside, he'll die.
他会死的，吉姆
He'll die, Jim.
为什么…
Why...
…为什么一定会在八天内死？解释清楚
...must he die? Why within eight days? Explain.
我不知道
I don't know.
你一直这么说，你不是个医生吗？
You keep saying that. Are you a doctor or aren't you?
他的机体失衡越来越严重
There's a growing imbalance of body functions.
就好像我们体内的肾上腺素
As if in our bodies, huge amounts of adrenaline
不断涌入血管
were constantly being pumped into our bloodstreams.
但是我的电脑不能追踪出来
Now, I can't trace it down in my bio-comps.
史波克不愿意告诉我是什么
Spock won't tell me what it is.
但是如果这种激素不停止
But if it isn't stopped somehow,
体能和精神上的压力会把他压垮致死的
the physical and emotional pressures will simply kill him.
你确定他知道是什么吗？
You say you're convinced he knows what it is?
是的
He does.
但他像毕宿五的贝类一样守口如瓶
And he's as tightlipped about it as an Aldebaran shellmouth.
问他没用的，吉姆，他不会说的
No use to ask him, Jim. He won't talk.
进来
Come.
不用起来
Stay.
麦考伊已经给我你的体检报告了
McCoy has given me his medical evaluation of your condition.
他说如果不采取行动的话你就会死
He says you're going to die unless something is done.
是什么？
What?
是只有你的母星能解救你？
Is it something only your planet can do for you?
史波克
Spock.
你是全舰队最好的大副
You've been called the best first officer in the Fleet.
你对我来说非常重要
That's an enormous asset to me.
如果我要失去一个大副，我要知道是为什么
If I have to lose that first officer, I want to know why.
这是一个没有外邦人知道的事情
It's a thing no outworlder may know...
除了那些少数被卷入其中的
...except those very few who've been involved.
瓦肯人知道，但是我们之间也不会提及
A Vulcan understands, but even we do not speak of it among ourselves.
这是一个非常私人的事情
It is a deeply personal thing.
你能明白吗，舰长？
Can you see that, Captain, and understand?
我不明白，解释给我听
No, I do not understand. Explain.
这是命令
Consider that an order.
有的事是超乎命令的
There are some things which transcend even the discipline of the service.
如果我告诉你
Would it help if I told you that I'll treat this
我会保守这个秘密的，你能告诉我吗？
as totally confidential?
这跟生理有关
It has to do with biology.
- 什么？ - 生理
- What? - Biology.
- 什么生理？ - 瓦肯生理
- What kind of biology? - Vulcan biology.
你的意思是，瓦肯人的生理？
You mean, the biology of Vulcans?
繁衍生理？
Biology as in reproduction?
呃…
Well...
没什么好害羞的，史波克先生
...there's no need to be embarrassed about it, Mr. Spock.
鸟类和蜂类也有这种情况
It happens to the birds and bees.
鸟和蜂不是瓦肯人，舰长
The birds and the bees are not Vulcans, Captain.
如果他们是
If they were,
如果任何生物像我们一样
if any creature as proudly logical as us,
有逻辑思维
were to have their logic
在这种时刻都会失去理智…
ripped from them as this time does to us...
瓦肯人怎么选择配偶？
How do Vulcans choose their mates?
你有想过吗？
Haven't you wondered?
我猜是…
I guess the rest of us assume that it's done...
…很理智的
...quite logically.
不
No.
不是的
It is not.
我们沿袭古老的
We shield it with ritual...
传统和习俗
...and customs shrouded in antiquity.
你们无法想象
You humans have no conception.
它剥夺我们的理智
It strips our minds from us.
剥下我们文明的外衣
It brings a madness which
使我们变得疯狂
rips away our veneer of civilisation.
这叫逄会
It is the Pon farr.
或者说交配时刻
The time of mating.
这是有自然的先例的，舰长
There are precedents in nature, Captain.
轩辕五的鸟鳗
The giant eel-birds of Regulus V,
每11年就会回到他们出生的洞穴
once each 11 years they must return to the caverns where they hatched.
地球上的鲑鱼
On your Earth, salmon.
他们必须回到那条小溪
They must return to that one stream
他们出生的地方繁殖
where they were born to spawn.
或者死去
Or die in trying.
但你不是鱼，史波克先生，你是…
But you're not a fish, Mr. Spock. You're...
不，我也不是人
No, nor am I a man.
我是瓦肯人
I'm a Vulcan.
我以为我能躲过这劫
I had hoped I would be spared this...
…但古老的欲望太强烈
...but the ancient drives are too strong.
最后会吞没我们
Eventually they catch up with us.
而我们无法控制这股力量…
And we are driven by forces we cannot control...
…然后回家…
...to return home...
…娶妻…
...and take a wife...
…或死去…
...or die.
我会当作什么都没听到的
I haven't heard a word you've said.
而且…
And...
我会想办法带你回瓦肯
I'll get you to Vulcan. Somehow.
上尉，帮我联系舰队司令部第九分队寇马克上将
Lieutenant, get me Admiral Komack at Starfleet Command, Sector 9.
接到麦考伊办公室
Pipe it down to McCoy's office.
舰队司令部，是，长官
Starfleet Command. Yes, sir.
苏鲁先生，你该不会认为…
Mr. Sulu, you don't think...
你也许该准备一条回瓦肯的路，以防万一
Maybe you ought to plot a course back to Vulcan, just in case.
联系史波克先生，我是乌乎拉上尉
Communication to Mr. Spock. Lieutenant Uhura here.
舰长让我通知你…
Captain asked me to inform you he is...
让我一个人静一静！
Let me alone!
舰长，你的要求并非寻常
Captain, you're making a most unusual request.
我知道，但是也非常重要
I'm aware of that, sir. But it's of the utmost importance.
您一定要批准我绕道去瓦肯
You must give me permission to divert to Vulcan.
但你拒绝解释为什么
But you refuse to explain why it is so important.
我不能解释，长官
I can't, sir.
但请相信我，我不会恳请…
But believe me, I wouldn't make such a request...
牛郎6号可不是个平常事
The Altair VI is no ordinary matter.
那地方好不容易在星际纷争后得以恢复
That area is just putting itself together after a long interplanetary conflict.
就职典礼会安抚整个牛郎星星系
This inauguration will stabilise the entire Altair system.
我们的出现是友谊的象征
Our appearance there is a demonstration of friendship
是对克林贡帝国有力的震慑
and strength which will cause ripples clear to the Klingon Empire.
先生…
Sir...
…我们绝对不会延迟超过一天，我不相信…
...the delay would be at most a day. I can hardly believe...
寇克，按照命令去牛郎6号
Kirk, you will proceed to Altair VI as ordered.
就这么说，执行你的命令，完毕
The subject is closed. You have your orders. Starfleet out.
- 看来只能这么办了 - 不
- Well, that's that. - No, it's not.
我明白牛郎星的局势
I know the Altair situation.
算上我们会有三艘星舰，气派而且带着外交使命
We would be one of three starships. Very impressive, very diplomatic.
但是没那么重要
It's simply not that vital.
你不能违背命令去瓦肯，你会被惩罚的…
You can't go off to Vulcan against Starfleet orders. You'll be busted...
我不能眼睁睁看着史波克死啊，老骨头
I can't let Spock die, can I, Bones?
如果我们去牛郎星他必死无疑
And he will if we go to Altair.
他救了我那么多次性命，难道不值我牺牲事业救他？
I owe him my life a dozen times over. Isn't that worth a career?
他是我的朋友
He's my friend.
- 舰桥，导航部 - 舰桥，导航部
- Bridge. Navigation. - Bridge. Navigation.
契诃夫先生…
Mr. Chekov...
…设计线路去瓦肯，告诉轮机部要曲速八或更快
...lay in a course for Vulcan. Tell Engineering I want warp 8 or better.
以最快速度前行
Push her for all she'll take.
线路已预备好，开始执行中，先生
Course already plotted. Laying it in, sir.
很好，契诃夫先生，寇克退出
I see. Very well. Carry on, Mr. Chekov. Kirk out.
查佩尔小姐？
Miss Chapel?
是，史波克先生？
Yes, Mr. Spock?
我做了一个…
I had...
…噩梦
...a most startling dream.
你在跟我说话…
You were trying to tell me something...
…但我听不见
...but I couldn't hear you.
跟自己的本性抗争…
It would be illogical for us to protest...
…是无谓的…
...against our natures...
…你觉得呢？
...don't you think?
我不理解
I don't understand.
你流泪了
Your face is wet.
我过来告诉你我们要去瓦肯星了
I came to tell you that we are bound for Vulcan.
过不了几天我们就到了
We'll be there in just a few days.
瓦肯
Vulcan.
- 查佩尔小姐 - 我叫克莉丝汀
- Miss Chapel. - My name is Christine.
我知道，克莉丝汀
Yes, I know, Christine.
你可以为我做点普罗米克汤吗？
Would you make me some of that plomeek soup?
当然，我非常愿意，史波克先生
Oh, I'd be very glad to do that, Mr. Spock.
舰桥
Bridge.
显然你已经猜到我的问题了，医生
It's obvious that you've surmised my problem, Doctor,
我钦佩你的洞察力
and my compliments on your insight.
舰长，瓦肯正发生一件大事
Captain, there is a thing that happens to Vulcans at this time,
非常疯狂，你应该会反感
almost an insanity, which you would no doubt find distasteful.
是吗？
Will I?
你已经对我的疯狂表现出极大的忍耐了
You've been most patient with my kinds of madness.
你可以和我一起去瓦肯站在我边上吗？
Then would you beam down to the planet surface and stand with me?
有一个简短的仪式
There is a brief ceremony.
- 我能被允许吗？ - 这是我的权利
- Is it permitted? - It is my right.
按照传统，男方可以由最好的朋友陪伴
By tradition, the male is accompanied by his closest friends.
谢谢，史波克先生
Thank you, Mr. Spock.
我也请求麦考伊陪我一起
I also request McCoy accompany me.
我的荣幸，先生
I shall be honoured, sir.
舰长…
Captain...
…我们正处于瓦肯的欢迎频段，先生
...we're standing by on Vulcan hailing frequencies, sir.
打开频道，上尉
Open channel, Lieutenant.
瓦肯中心，这里是联邦星舰进取号
Vulcan Space Central, this is the U.S.S. Enterprise
请求进入轨道
requesting permission to assume standard orbit.
联邦星舰进取号，批准进入
U.S.S. Enterprise from Vulcan Space Central, permission granted.
全体瓦肯欢迎你们
And from all of Vulcan, welcome.
- 史波克在吗？ - 我是史波克
- Is Commander Spock with you? - This is Spock.
请站好以激活中央显示屏
Stand by to activate your central viewer, please.
医生，发生什么事了？
Doctor, what's going on?
史波克
Spock.
是我
It is I.
提普灵
T'Pring.
离别却从未离去
Parted from me and never parted.
从未接触
Never and always touching...
但始终相联
...and touched.
我们在相约之地见面
We meet at the appointed place.
史波克，离别却从未离去
Spock. Parted from me and never parted.
从未接触但始终相联
Never and always touching and touched.
我等你
I await you.
- 她很漂亮，史波克先生，她是谁？ - 她是提普灵…
- She's lovely, Mr. Spock. Who is she? - She is T'Pring...
…我的妻子
...my wife.
这是我的乡土
This is the land of my family.
我的家族在此生存了2000个地球年
It has been held by us for more than 2000 Earth years.
这是我们库努卡里菲的地方
This is our place of Koon-ut-kal-if-fee.
他说库努什么？
He called it Koon-ut what?
他的意思是“婚姻或决斗”
He described it to me as meaning "marriage or challenge."
过去，瓦肯人要为爱人决斗
In the distant past, Vulcans killed to win their mates.
现在他们仍为此疯狂
And they still go mad at this time.
代价就是余生不再有感情
Perhaps the price they pay for having no emotions the rest of the time.
好地方，如果来点凉风就好了
Lovely. I wish the breeze were cooler.
是啊，我总算体会到“热得像瓦肯”的含义
Yeah. "Hot as Vulcan." Now I understand what that phrase means.
这里的大气比地球稀薄
The atmosphere is thinner than Earth.
不知道提普灵什么时候到
I wonder when his T'Pring arrives?
婚礼盛典要开始了
The marriage party approaches.
我听到他们了
I hear them.
婚礼盛典？我以为提普灵已经是你的妻子了
Marriage party? You said T'Pring was your wife.
是我们父母定的亲
By our parents' arrangement.
在我们只有7岁的时候
A ceremony...
举行过一个仪式
...while we were but 7 years of age.
与其说是婚礼，倒不如说是定亲
Less than a marriage, but more than a betrothal.
碰一下对方
One touches the other
接触到对方的思想
in order to feel each other's thoughts.
通过这样，我们的思想就被锁在一起
In this way, our minds were locked together.
时候到来…
So that at the proper time...
…我们就会被吸引到…
...we would both be drawn to...
…库努卡里菲
... Koon-ut-kal-if-fee.
老骨头，知道那是谁吗？
Bones, do you know who that is?
提咆
T'Pau.
是唯一一个拒绝联邦议会席位的人
The only person to ever turn down a seat in the Federation Council.
提咆？
T'Pau?
主持史波克的婚礼？
Officiating at Spock's wedding?
他从没提过他家族这么显赫
He never mentioned that his family was this important.
史波克…
Spock...
…我们的仪式是给外人看的吗？
...are our ceremonies for outworlders?
他们不是外人
They are not outworlders.
他们是我的朋友
They are my friends.
我有权这么做
I am permitted this.
我是寇克
This is Kirk.
夫人
Ma'am.
- 你叫？ - 伦纳德·麦考伊，夫人
- And thee are called? - Leonard McCoy, ma'am.
你把这些外人称作朋友
Thee names these outworlders "friends."
谁能负责他们的行为？
How does thee pledge their behaviour?
我以性命担保，提咆
With my life, T'Pau.
你们将要看到的是…
What thee are about to see...
…从远古流传下来的…
...comes down from the time of the beginning...
…亘古不变
...without change.
这是瓦肯的心，瓦肯的灵魂
This is the Vulcan heart. This is the Vulcan soul.
这是我们的生活方式
This is our way.
- 这是什么？发生什么了？ - 她选择了决斗
- What is it? What happened? - She chooses the challenge.
和他？
With him?
他是处理懦夫的
He acts only if cowardice is seen.
她会选择她的代表
She will choose her champion.
史波克？
Spock?
不要和他说话，寇克
Do not attempt to speak with him, Kirk.
他身陷普拉克托，血热
He is deep in the plak tow, the blood fever.
在他通过历练之前
He will not speak with thee again
不会和你说话的
until he has passed through what is to come.
如果你想离开…
If thee wishes to depart...
…现在就可以
...thee may leave now.
我们留下
We'll stay.
史波克果然没看错人
Spock chose his friends well.
夫人，我不理解
Ma'am, I don't understand.
你的意思是她拒绝了他？她不想要他？
Are you trying to say that she rejected him. That she doesn't want him?
他必须为她决斗，这是她的权利
He will have to fight for her. It is her right.
提普灵，你已经选择了卡里菲
T'Pring, thee has chosen the kal-if-fee...
…即决斗
...the challenge.
你准备好成为胜者的战利品吗？
Thee are prepared to become the property of the victor?
我准备好了
I am prepared.
史波克
Spock.
你愿意根据律法和传统接受挑战吗？
Does thee accept challenge, according to our laws and customs?
你觉得史波克能赢得了他吗？
You think Spock can take him?
我表示怀疑，他现在情况不佳
I doubt it. Not in his present condition.
提普灵，你选择你的代表
T'Pring, thee will choose thy champion.
生命之初
As it was in the dawn of our days,
就如今晨的黎明
as it is today
和所有的明天
as it will be for all tomorrows,
我选择
I make my choice.
他
This one.
不
No.
让我来
I am to be the one.
- 她答应过的 - 安静
- It was agreed. - Be silent.
听我说
Hear me.
我提出了古老的要求，我要求这个权利
I have made the ancient claim. I claim the right.
这个女人…
The woman is...
请宽恕
I ask forgiveness.
寇克…
Kirk...
…提普灵的要求是合理的，但我们的律法和传统
...T'Pring is within her rights, but our laws and customs...
…并不制约你
...are not binding on thee.
你可以自己决定…
Thee are free to decline...
我们不会强加于你
...with no harm on thyself.
提咆
T'Pau.
你开口了？
Thee speaks?
我的朋友…
My friend...
…并不了解
...does not understand.
决定已经做出了，史波克
The choice has been made, Spock.
由他来决定
It is up to him now.
他不了解情况
He does not know.
我会参加决斗，提咆
I will do what I must, T'Pau.
但绝不是和他决斗
But not with him.
他的血液不会燃烧
His blood does not burn.
他是我的朋友
He is my friend.
人们说瓦肯人的血是稀薄的
It is said thy Vulcan blood is thin.
你是瓦肯人还是人类？
Are thee Vulcan or are thee human?
我会燃烧，提咆
I burn, T'Pau.
我的眼睛就是火焰
My eyes are flame.
我的心脏就是火焰
My heart is flame.
你有权决定，提咆
Thee has the power, T'Pau.
以父之名，请禁止吧
In the name of my fathers, forbid.
提咆
T'Pau.
我请求你
I plead with thee.
我乞求你
I beg.
你已经用瓦肯传统证明了你自己
Thee has prided thyself on thy Vulcan heritage.
已经决定了
It is decided.
如果我拒绝，史波克会怎么样
What happens to Spock if I decline?
另一个代表会被选出与他决斗
Another champion will be selected.
不要干涉，寇克，不要乱动
Do not interfere, Kirk. Keep thy place.
你不能决斗，吉姆
You can't do it, Jim.
- 我不能？ - 不能
- I can't? - No.
她说你不受制于他们的律法和习俗
She said that their laws and customs were not binding on you.
但你说史波克可能打不过他
And you said Spock might not be able to handle him.
如果我能打晕史波克而不伤害他
Now, if I can knock Spock out without really hurting him.
在这样的天气？
In this climate?
就算不热死你也会呼吸不过来
If the heat doesn't get you, the thin air will.
你做不到的
You can't do it.
如果出了麻烦我就退出
If I get into any trouble, I'll quit.
那史波克赢，大不了丢面子
And Spock wins, and honour is satisfied.
- 吉姆，听我说，如果… - 老骨头
- Jim, listen, if you... - Bones.
他是我的大副也是我朋友
He's my first officer and my friend.
我违背了舰队的命令把他带到这
I disregarded Starfleet orders to bring him here.
还有，这是提咆，是瓦肯人
Another thing, that's T'Pau, a Vulcan.
所有瓦肯人都在这了
All of Vulcan in one package.
我怎么能在她面前退缩
How can I back out in front of her?
就这么决定了
It is done.
寇克，决定吧
Kirk, decide.
我接受挑战
I accept the challenge.
为争夺提普灵的
Here begins the act of combat
决斗开始
for possession of the woman T'Pring.
就好象时间之初，现也如此
As it was at the time of the beginning, so it is now.
把里尔耙带上来
Bring forth the lirpa.
如果他们在这关活下来…
If both survive the lirpa...
…那决斗就改用安乎
...combat will continue with the ahn'woon.
“如果都活下来”，什么意思
What do you mean, "if both survive"?
决斗以死结束
This combat is to the death.
等等，夫人
Now, wait a minute, ma'am.
谁说决斗以死结束了？
Who said anything about a fight to the death?
他们是朋友，强迫他们互相残杀
These men are friends. To force them to fight till one of them is killed...
我不允许你们再演这出了
I can forgive such a display only once.
决斗已经提出，并已依法接受
Challenge was given and lawfully accepted.
决斗已经开始了
It has begun.
不准任何人干预
Let no one interfere.
史波克，不要！
Spock, no!
这是瓦肯的骑士精神吗？
Is this Vulcan chivalry?
空气对寇克来说太热太稀薄了，他适应不了
The air is too hot and thin for Kirk. He's not used to it.
空气如此有什么办法
The air is the air. What can be done?
我可以用这个弥补空气不足和高温
I can compensate for the atmosphere and the temperature with this.
至少给寇克一个战斗的机会
At least it will give Kirk a fighting chance.
准
Thee may proceed.
你必须杀了他，吉姆
You're going to have to kill him, Jim.
杀了史波克？
Kill Spock?
这不是我们来瓦肯的目的，不是吗？
That's not what we came to Vulcan for, is it?
这是什么？
What's that?
这是三氧复合剂，能帮助你呼吸
It's a tri-ox compound. It'll help you breathe.
- 小心点 - 谨遵医嘱
- Now be careful. - Sound medical advice.
上安乎
The ahn'woon.
放手，史波克
Get your hands off of him, Spock.
结束了
It's finished.
他死了
He's dead.
请节哀
I grieve with thee.
- 麦考伊请求联系进取号 - 进取号乌乎拉在此
- McCoy to Enterprise. - Enterprise. Lieutenant Uhura here.
请传送室准备传送登陆小队
Have the Transporter Room stand by to beam up the landing party.
虽然很讽刺，但是史波克先生，由你下命令了
As strange as it may seem, Mr. Spock, you're in command now.
有什么指令吗？
Any orders?
有
Yes.
我一会儿就跟上你们
I'll follow you up in a few minutes.
你让契诃夫先生
You will instruct Mr. Chekov
设计一条去最近星际基地的线路
to plot a course for the nearest star base...
…我要在那里向当局自首
...where I must surrender myself to the authorities.
提普灵
T'Pring.
- 解释一下 - 解释什么
- Explain. - Specify.
为什么要决斗
Why the challenge.
为什么你选择我的舰长做代表
And why you chose my captain as your champion.
我和斯通两情相悦
Stonn wanted me, I wanted him.
我不明白，你为什么会喜欢他而不喜欢我
I see no logic in preferring Stonn over me.
你是个名人，史波克
You have become much known among our people, Spock.
甚至说是传奇
Almost a legend.
时间流转
And as the years went by,
我意识到我不想成为一个传奇的配偶
I came to know that I did not want to be the consort of a legend.
但是根据律法，我只能通过卡里菲和你离婚
But by the laws of our people, I could only divorce you by the kal-if-fee.
当然还有斯通的原因，他很爱慕我
There was also Stonn, who wanted very much to be my consort,
我也爱慕他
and I wanted him.
如果你的舰长赢了，他不会要我
If your captain were victor, he would not want me
那我就可以拥有斯通
and so I would have Stonn.
如果你赢了，你会放我走，因为我选择了决斗
If you were victor, you would free me because I had dared to challenge
那我还能和斯通在一起
and again I would have Stonn.
即使你没放了我，那也一样
But if you did not free me, it would be the same.
你会离开
For you would be gone,
我拥有你的名分和财产
and I would have your name and your property,
而斯通仍在这里
and Stonn would still be there.
非常有逻辑性
Logical.
完美无瑕的逻辑
Flawlessly logical.
- 谢谢 - 斯通
- I am honoured. - Stonn.
她是你的了
She is yours.
过一段时间，你会发现拥有…
After a time, you may find that having...
并不像爱慕一样让人开心
...is not so pleasing a thing after all as wanting.
这解释不通…
It is not logical...
…但确是事实
...but it is often true.
我是史波克，请传送我
Spock here. Stand by to beam up.
生生不息，繁荣昌盛，提咆
Live long, T'Pau, and prosper.
生生不息，繁荣昌盛，史波克
Live long and prosper, Spock.
恐怕我都做不到了
I shall do neither.
我杀了我的舰长和我的朋友
I have killed my captain and my friend.
传送
Energize.
医生，我想辞职
Doctor, I shall be resigning my commission immediately, of course.
所以我会感激你能做最后的安排
So I would appreciate your making the final arrangements.
- 史波克，我… - 医生，请听我说完
- Spock, I... - Doctor, please, let me finish.
我的罪行没有借口
There can be no excuse for the crime of which I am guilty.
我不想狡辩
I intend to offer no defence.
另外，我会请史考特立刻接手舰船
Furthermore, I will order Mr. Scott to take immediate command of this vessel.
- 难道你不应该先和我打个招呼吗？ - 舰长
- Shouldn't you check with me first? - Captain.
吉姆！
Jim!
见到你很高兴，舰长
I'm pleased to see you, Captain.
你看起来没事
You seem uninjured.
我有点搞不清了
I am at something of a loss to understand it, however.
怪麦考伊吧
Blame McCoy.
他给我注射的不是三氧复合剂
That was no tri-ox compound he shot me with.
是一种模拟死亡的麻醉剂
He slipped in a neural paralyzer. Knocked me out. Simulated death.
- 确实如此 - 护士，你介意给我们点空间吗？
- Indeed. - Nurse, would you mind, please?
史波克，婚礼和那个女孩后来怎么样？
Spock, what happened down there? The girl, the wedding?
哦，对了，那个女孩
Oh, yes, the girl.
有意思的是我在决斗的时候
Most interesting. It must have been the combat.
当我杀了舰长后，对提普灵完全失去了兴趣
When I thought I had killed the Captain, I found I'd lost all interest in T'Pring.
那种疯狂也消失了
The madness was gone.
- 寇克在此 - 寇克舰长
- Kirk here. - Captain Kirk.
来自舰队指挥部的消息，最高优先级
Message from Starfleet Command. Top priority.
转播过来，上尉
Relay it, Lieutenant.
应提咆的要求，进取号绕道去瓦肯的行动
Response to T'Pau's request for diversion of Enterprise to Vulcan
予以批准，迟到不予追究
hereby approved. Any reasonable delay granted.
寇马克上将，舰队指挥部
Komack, Admiral, Starfleet Command.
迟到一点，但能被赦免太好了
A little late, but I'm glad they're seeing it our way.
还是提咆的影响大，他们不能拒绝她的请求
How about that T'Pau? They couldn't turn her down.
契诃夫先生
Mr. Chekov,
设计好线路去牛郎星6号，准备好即刻出发，寇克退出
lay in a course for Altair VI. Leave orbit when ready. Kirk out.
还有一件事，史波克先生
There's just one thing, Mr. Spock,
别告诉我你看到吉姆还活着的时候
you can't tell me when you saw Jim alive,
你没有激动得想要跳起来
you weren't on the verge of giving an emotional scene
激动得要把马都拉倒
that would've brought the house down.
只是理智上的解脱
Merely my quite logical relief
还好舰队没有失去这样一位高水平的舰长
that Starfleet had not lost a highly proficient captain.
- 很好，史波克先生，我理解 - 谢谢，舰长
- Yes, Mr. Spock. I understand. - Thank you, Captain.
当然，史波克，你的反应很理智
Of course, Mr. Spock. Your reaction was quite logical.
谢谢，医生
Thank you, Doctor.
在傻子眼里
In a pig's eye.
走吧，史波克，去仓库看看
Come on, Spock. Let's go mind the store.
TLF字幕组欢迎你，欢迎有志之士加入
TLF中文字幕站http://tlfsubs.eastgame.org/